Finding Aid for Joseph L. Sax Papers, 1943-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- that vested interests not be included in such a way that they could interfere with an excellent decision-making process ...
The earlier activity by the Senate came in the Senate Conservation Committee on June 4th. Here the controversial amendment changing the word "and" to "or" was accepted, (The bond was also increased to $500). on the 11th of June, the Senate Conservation and Tourist Industry Committee reported out a bill with a provision for an increased security bond and with a strong statement regarding review of existing standards. In the two weeks between this activity and the final Senate vote several editorials for and against the Act were aired on local stations.[6] Meanwhile a coalition backing the strong version of the Act was assembled, and environmentalists went to Lansing to picket on the Capitol lawn in its support. Representatives Anderson and Goemaere and State Senators George Fitzgerald (the Democratic Senate leader), John McCauley and Roger Craig addressed the crowd. Senator Levin expressed his determination to fight off all weakening amendments to the Act including the alternative defense ("and" to "or") and the insertion of the word "unreasonable" (before every instance of the words "pollution, impairment or destruction").
Final Events
Favorable consideration came in the Senate on the 26th of June. There the debate addressed many of the questions that had been raised by interest groups for the last year and half (summarized earlier in this history). The Senate passed a relatively uncompromised version by a vote of 34-3 and sent it to the House for consideration of 7 amendments. The most important of these spelled out collateral estoppel and res judicata and raised the security bond to $500. Votes against the bill were registered by Senators Hungerford, who expressed concern. about absence of due process under the legislation; Lockwood who adopted the 1969 Attorney General opposition to the bill; and Huber, who considered the MEPA an improper solution to important environmental problems. The Governor immediately commended the Senate for its activity and urged speedy House concurrence in it.
The House could not work with more speed. It approved the Senate amendments by a vote of 79-2 within minutes after receiving the Senate version and sent the bill to Governor Milliken. In fact Rule 59 (that a bill lie over 1 day upon receipt by the other Chamber) was suspended.
Ironically, Representative Goemaere voted against the bill. He attacked the addition of Senator Rockwell's name to the official style of the law. Senator Hungerford's first "no" vote as a Senator was more substantive:
It is my belief that if every individual is permitted to file for damages, every do-gooder, kook, psychopath or malcontent will file so many actions that our already over-burdened judicial system will be in danger of breaking down.
Governor Milliken again commended the legislature and stated that there will now be "no privileged sanctuaries for polluters in Michigan". He indicated that he would sign the bill.
On July 14th, 1970 MEPA was presented to the Governor. The "Thomas J. Anderson, Gordon Rockwell., Environmental Protection Act of 1970" was signed on July 27, 1970, to take immediate effect. A new chapter of Michigan law had begun.
_________________________
Notes
1 -- The Council's position may have been influenced by knowledge of a model for environmental protection encompassed in a California bill that would create a California Environmental Study Council. Dr. Harold "Ted" Black of the Michigan Department of Natural Resources had sent Mrs. Wolfe a copy of the bill on January 8, 1969.
2 -- Page numbers refer to unofficial transcript of debate in box 2, file 3, transcribed Mrs. Margaret White, Summer, 1980.
3 -- Other recommendations for changes appear in the collection in Box 1 ("Versions of the Michigan Environmental Protection Act") and some are discussed in detail in the following section.
4 -- The building blocks for the MEPA are summarized in an early hand-written note found in the Bentley Papers. On these sheets Professor Sax jotted down the pieces that would combine in the Michigan Act. His notes addressed the powers of the Water Resources Commission; mentioned qui tam actions, defined prima facie, recognized the existence of feasible and prudent alternative 1anguage in other legislation, noted the existence of wildlife preserves in New Jersey, and anticipated some common questions in suits brought by neighbors against neighbors. The scribbled ideas also recognized the existence of anti-trust triple damages law. But damages were never considered remedies under the Michigan Environmental Protection Act. Analysis was offered through consideration of the bill.
5 -- Earlier in April a 78-21 vote had adopted the amendment requiring a $300 bond. It was at that time that the House rejected another crippling change in the MEPA. By a vote of 62-38 an amendment was rejected that stated that where "standards of pollution are provided by law, they shall form the basis of determining pollution under this act."
6 -- Newspaper coverage of consideration of the bill was extensive and scored the adversarial nature of the passage of MEPA. Part of MEPA's history is told in the headlines of the time. (Box 1, files 23-23)
"Man Faces Extinction; Dingell".
"Defending the Environment" (Sunday Magazine)
"Pollution Fighters Rally for Bill"
"Hope for Citizens to Fight Pollution" (Free Press)
"State Politicians Jump to Join Pollution Fight" (Free Press)
The collection is arranged in nine series: Correspondence; House Bill 3055; House Bill 5054; Environmental Protection Legislation; Michigan Environmental Protection Act Case Files; Case Files; Teaching Materials; Travels and Lectures; and Publications and Research.
Organization and Classification of Papers in the Collection
There are several ways of classifying the material in the MEPA collection. We decided on a format that would minimize the amount of interpretation we imposed upon the collection. This may be desirable from the point of view of scholars who will work with these materials in the future. From a practical point of view it was necessary as well. Further classification would require considerable subjective judgment. For example, to catalogue according to amount of support of or opposition to the MEPA would involve separating the author's desired political effect of a statement from literal wording. Many documents which begin with praise of the general principle of the legislation seemed to be clearly aimed at weakening the law to the point of effectively defeating it.
Our coding scheme for primary commentary on MEPA thus is quite simple:
Individual or Corporate Actor (from which we decided to separate out the papers of Joseph Sax)
Interest groups
Governmental Entities
Elected officials
We also have distinguished among materials by using the following symbols in the file summaries (explained below).
T - testimony
Ba - bill analysis
P - policy paper
A few additional comments on the collection are in order:
We have included our working data (file) summaries in the first folder of each category. These may be of sonic, value to the researcher who needs to investigate a particular point or issue. We do not consider these a complete index to the materials, but rather offer them as a preliminary summary of the data. They can assist in finding classes of materials (such as analyses by state agencies) and particular documents (such as testimony by individuals).
In the collection materials are generally filed according to the code of the initiator of the document. Thus a letter from Mrs. Wolfe representing the West Michigan Environmental Action Council (interest group) to Representative Thomas Anderson (elected official) is found in the interest group folder. However the Sax folders contain correspondence to and from Professor Sax in order to allow for easier access to what some will consider very significant correspondence in the history of' the Act.
The Joseph L. Sax papers comprise a comprehensive collection of legislative history and documentation on the enactment of the "Thomas J. Anderson, Gordon Rockwell Environmental Protection Act of 1970" (MEPA). MEPA was originally drafted by Professor Joseph L. Sax of the University of Michigan Law School and was one of the first projects undertaken by the Law School's Environmental Law Society.
The papers collected herein should be useful to several groups. Students of the environmental movement have herein a rich source of information on the early activities of the movement in Michigan and the philosophies behind various-approaches to environmental control. Lawyers interested in the legislative history of the MEPA will find an extensive collection of documents tracing the bill's movement through a number of committees of the Michigan House and Senate. Arguments about many of the issues that continue to be raised in MEPA litigation are presented in full detail in materials in these files. Students of government and political science may discover documentation of value in studies of interest group politics and the legislative process. Other uses, not imagined by those who assembled this collection, no doubt will be made.
The project was motivated in part by requests made of Professor Sax and others by lawyers, historians, and legislators in the United States and abroad about the background of the Michigan Act. Professor Sax feared that the documents that he had collected, many of which are unique and irreplaceable, might begin to be scattered and/or deteriorate. Later, it was decided to supplement Sax's papers by assembling all available documentation in the state on the Michigan Environmental Protection Act. Materials in this collection trace the history of the Act from the first correspondence between the West Michigan Environmental Action Council and Professor Sax requesting that he draft a model environmental law, through the passage of the law by the Michigan Legislature and its signing by Governor Milliken on July 27th, 1970. The collection also contains post-enactment materials, including attempts to amend the bill, through April 1976. Plans are underway to add to the collection all relevant legislative and judicial documents relating to the law, its interpretation and amendment.
Highlights of the collection include the following: the original correspondence between Professor Sax and Mrs. Joan Wolfe relating to the idea for the drafting of a model environmental law in Michigan; correspondence on MEPA from the files of Representative Thomas Anderson in which he indicates his early hopes for and concerns over the Act and his strategy for shepherding the bill through the Michigan Legislature; various versions and drafts of the bill; analyses of the bill by the Governor's office and state agencies; and testimony delivered at public hearings on the bill. Also in the collection is a tape of the Senate Debate on the bill. (A complete listing of materials in the collection is found at the end of this document.)
Several sources contributed to this collection. The great majority of the material comes from the papers of Professor Joseph L. Sax on the passage of the Act and attempts to amend it. In addition, papers of Mrs. Joan Wolfe (who also has another collection in the Bentley Historical Library) were solicited and added. These include communications of the West Michigan Environmental Action Council at various points in the legislative consideration of the Act. Attorney General Frank Kelley indicated in a reply to a request for MEPA materials that most of the relevant documentation of the Department of the Attorney General on the Act had already been forwarded (courtesy copies) to Professor Sax. Requests were also made of the Executive office of the Governor, the Secretary of the Michigan Senate, and the West Michigan Environmental Action Council; any contributions from them will be added to the files when received.
An important supplemental source of information on the Act was found in Representative Thomas J. Anderson's papers on the MEPA in the State Archives of the Michigan History Division, Michigan Department of State: Personal papers, Thomas J. Anderson, [74-22, Accession boxes 403, 404, 405(B)]. Other materials from the State Archives were reviewed to insure that the MEPA Collection would be complete for legislative history and research on the State's environmental movement. Of relevance were House of Representatives, Standing Committees' Public Hearings, 1969-1973, [RG79-37, Lot 43, Box 1.) and House Committee, 1969-70, Conservation and Recreation [72-34, Lot 21, Box 4 and Box 51.
The State Archives material was not duplicated in total for this collection. Rather, those materials which record a significant event in the movement of the bill through the Michigan Legislature or highlight an important position on the bill by an interest group or governmental entity were reproduced for inclusion here.[7]Representative Anderson, who was the prime legislative mover in the passage of MEPA, received over 8000 letters or petitions about H.B. 3055. Many of these are included in his papers and are not found herein. Our efforts aimed to add to the Bentley Collection documentation from the Archives that would be of major interest to legal and history scholars.
[Archive material is noted in the files by a penciled asterisk (*) on the upper right hand corner of the document.]
Archive materials relating to MEPA after its passage were not searched for this study; there are several folders of post enactment materials and other relevant files in the Archives (e.g. 74-22 B405 FL "Newsclippings relating to H.B. 305511).
In 1982, the library received additional materials regarding the Michigan Environmental Protection Act. This new material collected by Professor Joseph Sax largely concerns similar kinds of legislation enacted in other states. Included are correspondence and legislative materials
In 1986, the library received an additional 13 feet of material, mainly case files detailing litigation arising out of the Act. The most important of these cases was perhaps the so-called Pigeon River case (West Michigan, Environmental Action Council v. Natural Resources Commission).
In 2014, the library received an additional 16 feet of material. This addition is organized into four series: Case Files, Teaching Materials, Travels and Lectures, and Publications and Research. Each series is further arranged in chronological order by year. Additional material related to this accession has been added to the Correspondence and Related Materials series, which includes correspondence from 1986-1998, a diary from a 1979 visit to Japan, and a copy of the finding aid from the American Heritage Center's Joseph L. Sax papers.
Subjects:
Animas-La Plata Project.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Cultural property.; Cultural property--Protection--Law and legislation.; Environmental impact analysis--Law and legislation.; Environmental impact analysis--Michigan.; Environmental law.; Environmental law--Cases.; Environmental policy--United States.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Michigan. Michigan Environmental Protection Act (1970); Legal consultants.; National parks and reserves--United States.; Pigeon River Country State Forest (Mich.); Public lands--Recreational use.; Riparian rights--United States.; Southern Nevada Water Authority.; University of California, Berkeley--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Water rights.; Wildlife management.
Genres:
Audiotapes.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence and Related Materials
  - Correspondence relating to the Joseph Sax collection (Box 1)
    [1]
  - American Heritage Center Finding Aid 1972-1989 (Box 33)
  - Meetings and memos 1994 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence 1986-1998 (Box 34)
  - Japan diary 1979 (Box 34)
- H.B. 3055
  - Correspondence, Testimony, Policy Statements, Bill Analysis etc
    - Joseph R. Sax
      - April 28, 1969-December 12, 1969 (Box 1)
        [2]
      - January 6, 1970-April 1, 1970 (Box 1)
        [3]
      - April 2, 190-December 3 1970 (Box 1)
        [4]
      - Undated (Box 1)
        [5]
    - Individuals and Corporate Actors
      - January 19, 1970-Fb. 25 1970 (Box 1)
        [6]
      - February 26, 190-May 15 1970 (Box 1)
        [7]
      - May 18, 1970-July 29, 1970, undated (Box 1)
        [8]
    - Interest Groups
      - March 18, 1969-Fb. 27 1970 (Box 1)
        [9]
      - March 3, 1970-May 21, 1970 (Box 1)
        [10]
      - May 22, 1970-July 29, 1970, undated (Box 1)
        [11]
    - Government
      - Jan 8, 1969-February 27,1970 (Box 1)
        [12]
      - March 5, 1970-July 21, 1970, undated (Box 1)
        [13]
    - Elected Officials
      - May 7, 1969-February 27, 1970 (Box 1)
        [14]
      - March 2, 1970-June 16, 1970 (Box 1)
        [15]
      - June 26, 1970-October 6, 1970, undated (Box 1)
        [16]
  - Versions of the Michigan Environmental Protection Act
    - Original Bill, undated 1969-April 1, 1970 (Box 1)
      [17]
    - Substitute House Bill No.3055 reported out March, 25 1970 (Box 1)
      [18]
    - Second Substitute for H.B. 3055 (Box 1)
    - Second Substitute for H.B. 3055 as amended by the House (Box 1)
      [19]
    - Second Substitute for H.B. 3055 as passed by House of Representatives April 21, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Enrolled House Bill No. 3055 Michigan Compiled Laws Annotated, Section 691.1201 et. seq. (Box 1)
      [20]
    - Journal of the House of Representatives of the State of Michigan 1970 Regular Session, Substitute Bills (Box 1)
    - Proposed Amendments
      - March 4, 1970, March 5, 1970, March 6, 1970, March 13, 1970, March 25, 1970, undated (Box 1)
        [21]
      - April 2, 1970 April 21, 1970 (Box 1)
        [22]
  - Newspaper and other coverage of the Act
    - March 1969-January 21. 1970 (Box 1)
      [23]
    - January 22, 1970-January 28, 1970 (Box 1)
      [24]
    - February 1, 1970-April 13, 1970 (Box 1)
      [25]
    - April 15, 1970-April 24, 1970 (Box 1)
      [26]
    - May 1, 1970-June 8, 1970 (Box 1)
      [27]
    - June 11, 1970-June 29, 1970, undated (Box 1)
      [28]
    - Post-passage (Box 2)
  - Michigan Supreme Court Ray Opinion
    - Copy of Opinion 1975 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Audio-tapes
    - Senate Debate and roll call on Michigan Environmental Act, 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Unofficial Transcripts of tapes (Box 2)
  - Interview with Joseph L. Sax by Paul Sabatier May 25, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Literature on Michigan Environmental Protection Act
    - August 10, 1970-December, 1970 (Box 2)
    - April 6 1971-May 1972 (Box 2)
    - September 9, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-February 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - July 30, 1976, undated (Box 2)
    - E. Haskell and V. Price Managing the Environment: Nine States Look for New Answers, 1971 (Box 2)
    - J.F. DiMento, Administrative Agency Response to Innovative Environmental Legislation (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Michigan) 1974 (Box 2)
    - J.F. DiMento Managing Environmental Change, A Legal and Behavioral Perspective, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Periodical Coverage of the Act
      - January 1970-August 1, 1970 (Box 3)
      - August 8 1970-February 1972 (Box 3)
      - January 31 1974-July 1975 (Box 3)
- House Bill 5054
  - Correspondence, Testimony, and related material
    - Joseph L. Sax
      - May 12, 1975-June 12, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 12, 1975-July 25, 1975 (Box 3)
      - August 11, 1975-September 23, 1975 (Box 3)
      - September 26, 1975-October 7, 1975 (Box 3)
      - October 9, 1975-October 20, 1975 (Box 3)
      - October 21, 1975-December 18, 1975, undated
    - Individual or Corporate Actor
      - April 17, 1975-June 3, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 4-8, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 9-11, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 12, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 13, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 14-16, 197 (Box 3)
      - June 17, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 18-19, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June20-24 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 26-October 31, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
    - Interest Groups
      - May 30, 1975-June 6, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 9-27, 1975 (Box 3)
      - July 11-August 4, 1975 (Box 3)
      - August 5-September 18, 1975 (Box 3)
      - September 25-November 24, 1975, undated (Box 3)
    - Government
      - May 13-October 10, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Elected Officials
      - June 13-20, 1975 (Box 3)
      - June 26-November 20, 1975 (Box 3)
        [29]
      - December 15-17, 1975, undated (Box 3)
        [30]
  - Text of Bills
    - H.B. 5054 S.B.699, and related amendments (Box 3)
      [31]
  - Newspaper Articles
    - April 20-May 12, 1975 (Box 3)
      [32]
    - June 2-5, 1975 (Box 3)
      [33]
    - June 6-13, 1975 (Box 3)
      [34]
    - June 15-30, 1975 (Box 3)
      [35]
    - July 2-24, 1975 (Box 3)
      [36]
    - July 25-31, 1975 (Box 3)
      [37
    - August 2-8, 1975 (Box 3)
      [38]
    - August 9-16, 1975 (Box 3)
      [39]
    - August 17-September 24, 1975 (Box 3)
      [40]
    - September 30-Oct 10 1975 (Box 3)
      [41]
    - October 12-November 11, 1975 (Box 3)
      [42]
    - November 11, 1975-December 9, 1975 (Box 3)
      [43]
    - December 10 1975-April 1976 (Box 3)
      [44]
  - Post-Enactment Amendment material
    - S.B. 1262, S.B. 1474, S.B.1119 (Box 3)
      [45]
    - H.B. 24630 Carr Amendments; S.B. 751; H.B. 5055; H.B. 5702 (Box 3)
      [46]
- Environmental Protection Legislation
  - Correspondence (Geographical)
    - Canada (Box 4)
    - United States
      - Alabama to Indiana (Box 4)
      - Kentucky to Minnesota (Box 4)
      - Missouri to New York (Box 4)
      - North Dakota to Rhode Island (Box 4)
      - South Carolina to Texas (Box 4)
      - Vermont to Wisconsin (Box 4)
  - Legislative Material
    - S.B.1032 (Box 4)
    - S.B.3575 (Box 4)
    - H.B. 56 (Box 4)
    - H.B. 2288 (Box 4)
    - H.B. 5076 (Box 4)
    - H.B. 11896 (Box 4)
    - ATLA Bill (Box 4)
    - Current Developments: Citizen's Suits 1975 (Box 4)
- Michigan Environmental Protection Act Case Files
  - First series
    - A-C (Box 5)
    - C-K (Box 6)
    - K-M (Box 7)
    - M-N (Box 8)
    - O-R (Box 9)
    - R-S (Box 10)
    - T-W (Box 11)
    - W (Box 12)
    - Pigeon River Case (West Michigan Environmental Action Council v. Natural Resources Commission) (Box 13)
    - Pigeon River Case (West Michigan Environmental Action Council v. Natural Resources Commission) (Box 14)
      (continued)
    - Pigeon River Case (West Michigan Environmental Action Council v. Natural Resources Commission) (Box 15)
  - Second Series
    - A-K (Box 15)
    - K-W (Box 16)
    - W-Z (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Published Material (Box 17)
- Case Files
  The Case Files series (1956-2013, 7 linear feet) contains materials related to Sax's career as a legal consultant on environmental issues. The majority of the materials are correspondence and research notes. In addition there is digital content relating to the Imperial Irrigation District's water rights to the Colorado River.
  - Colorado River Storage Project Act legislative History 1956 (Box 18)
  - Yosemite 1975 (Box 18)
  - Salt Lake City Meeting on Nuclear Waste Dump 1984 (Box 18)
  - Yellowstone 1985 (Box 18)
  - Animas-La Plata
    - 1988-1996 (Box 18)
    - Documents 1988 (Box 18)
    - 1996 (Box 18)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 18)
    - Alternatives 1996 (Box 18)
    - Romer/Schoettler Process 1997 (Box 18)
    - 1996-1997, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Imperial Irrigation District 1992, .ZIP files
    (Contains memos and speeches associated with the Imperial Irrigation District's water rights to the Colorado River case.)
  - Land and Water fund of the Rockies 1993-1994 (Box 19)
  - Oregon Water Legislation 1993 (Box 19)